we've all heard an athlete that's really
explosive fast or powerful be described
as fast which we've heard sayings like
this athlete can jump so high or lift so
much weight they must be made up of
super fast fibers they must have a lot
of these quick twitch fibers well it
seems to be a topic that a lot of people
are interested in and it's personally
had me excited for a couple of decades
now so I wanted to take the time and
explain to you a lot of the things that
I've learned over the last several
decades of studying this topic so you
have a better understanding of what
things like fast twitch quick twitch
slow twitch actually mean and whether or
not they matter to performance at all a
lot of us are have a rudimentary
understanding of how muscle works such
that our muscles our muscles are
comprised of a bunch of individual
muscle fibers that contract and produce
movement and so we understand that some
of our fibers are fast twitch and some
of them are slow twitch but where we
tend to fall off or the biggest argument
happens is the fundamental question of
okay well can these fibers change in
other words I have an athlete that jumps
really high she must have a lot of quick
twitch fibers she was she born that way
or can her fibers change based on her
training and so depending on where
you're at and whether you're a student
right now as an undergraduate you're not
involved in school at all never been to
school you're 50 years old you're an
accountant you just like training and
you like the website so you find this
topic interesting you may have heard
different things so I wanted to take
some time today and we will take quite
some time today to explore this area so
you have a better understanding of that
just flat out so you know the answer so
some of you have probably heard things
like
well first of all some of you've
probably heard no you can't change all
right you've got what you've got you're
born to be a certain way and there's no
changing others have described different
scenarios in which okay maybe for
example you're born with a certain
amount but there is some certain amount
of plasticity
others yet describe it okay that you're
born with a certain amount there's a
certain level of plasticity but it only
happens in one direction so one common
popular or common thing I hear is okay
you can change from fast twitch to slow
twitch so in other words you can convert
your fast twitch fibers in aslam judge
fibers but you can't go the other way so
you can't make new fast twitch fibers
and people typically use that to
describe why someone can never get that
much faster so why a normal person could
never outrun usain bolt because you're
saying simply born with that Mitch that
that more fast twitch fibers that many
more all right so we're gonna dive into
all of that today but the problem is
whether you and I love this cartoon here
and I'll give props to Jim Nuttall and
incorporated or whoever made this
cartoon I think it's phenomenal
but what we have is people over here in
one side that are getting their
textbooks out and they're saying look
the science shows this and they're
arguing you can change or you can't
change and they're probably arguing with
someone else who just searched the
Internet and we all love the Internet
searchers right and you've read a couple
of wikipedia pages and now for some how
or some reason you're an expert in the
topic but there's fighting back and
forth and there's fighting within those
fields and poor you right you can see
yourself down here you just stuck in the
middle you like you know what I don't
think care I don't want to read a
dissertation about this I don't really
want to go to 17 conferences and have to
read all these scientific papers I just
kind of want to be in the middle here
not I want to write down the answer so
we'll get to that today and we'll be
very clear about what it is and in fact
I want to be very clear right now about
what you're gonna get out of this it's
epic voyage you're about to go on
because this is gonna be a doozy it'll
be fun though and I promise I'll keep
you entertained so when you finish this
video or this series of videos you're
gonna have three very distinct things in
hand number one you're gonna understand
what these fiber types actually are and
to do that you're gonna understand a lot
more about what muscles really are and
how they work to we will definitely
answer the question of do muscle fiber
types change with exercise in humans and
number three we'll understand a little
bit more about why the confusion exists
now we're gonna be here for a while so
we're gonna actually cover quite a bit
more than that but that's just a start
in order to understand what muscle fiber
types are I think it's important we take
a step back all the way to the beginning
where we first started to understand
what muscle actually is so if we go all
the way back to the late
1960s and we start to find researchers
like Stenson and Lorenzini and we first
started describing and noticing that hey
some muscles and animals look different
in fact I think they believe in
Lorenzini first study looked at rabbit
muscle I started to realize hmm some of
their muscles are white and some of them
are red we actually started to notice
that the white ones and the red ones
contract differently when we fast
forward about 25 years to one of my
favorite scientists of all time
Anton van Leeuwenhoek who was credited
for the most part of developing the
microscope and he started actually
studying fish and I believe this initial
drawing was from cod they have to
remember he's looking through this
microscope this is the actual one on the
screen here that he used and he's
looking down at the muscle fibers of
these cons here he was starting to
describe and circle them this is
actually what we call a cross-section he
started to notice some fibers are bigger
some are smaller some of them have
different shape than the other ones
perhaps this is what determines or leads
to different types of contractions or
contractile properties
he also I think and a better one this is
from whale tissue I believe he started
to describe the fact that in fact when
we have a whole muscle so my entire
bicep or mine one of the muscles in my
quadricep what's actually happening
there is that muscle function is a
composite of all these millions of
individual muscle fibers so what you're
seeing in this beautiful drawing here is
four individual muscle fibers you can
actually see the connective tissue here
and here seeing there and there and the
fibers are running actually top to
bottom and so there would be you know
several million other fibers just like
this laying next to each other and those
would all be comprised together and
that's what would actually make up one
muscle so what he initially laid the
groundwork for here was in fact whole
muscle function how fast how strong how
much endurance I haven't in one of my
individual muscles is simply a composite
of the contractile abilities of all of
those individual muscle fibers
crazy to think this was in this in 1712
well fast forward a couple of hundred
years and it took about that much time
to have the next big innovation in this
field
and we had a famous scientists named
ranvier and if you're in the exercise
physiology world if you're an
undergraduate you're gonna get to this
in your ex physics class around VA I'm
sure you'll hear about him and if you're
a graduate student in this field that
name should spark
some some memory there but ranvier was
really the first one that came and said
oh okay we know that there were some
muscles that were red and white and that
determined their contractile differences
now we're finding some individual muscle
fibers are red and white and that's what
I'm depicting and in these graphs here
and I'm gonna use these little cartoons
to describe what an individual muscle
fiber is throughout the rest of the
presentation so when you see one of
these cylinders like this this would be
slow this would be excuse me a fast
twitch or a white muscle fiber and this
would be the opposite of a slow twitch
red muscle fiber but we knew that and in
fact up to 1873 this is all we knew is
some were red some are white and it
wasn't until years later we actually
identified that and started calling them
slow twitch or fast twitch so to
summarize up to 1900 we basically had
two answers we had we knew that
vertebrates had two different fiber
types and we knew that red were slower
than white but we really didn't
understand anything past that until
about the 1950s now this is really
amazing because at this time several
people in the 30s 40s and 50s developed
what's now called or what was initially
called the histo chemistry society but
it was basically an organization of
chemists that came together that we're
all interested in this same topic of
histochem entities so histology mixed
with chemistry which is kind of a fancy
way of saying we are interested in using
chemistry to study individual cells now
these people weren't interested in
muscle in human skeletal muscle because
they didn't have access to yet so almost
all of the wonderful work done in this
era was done in animals particularly
things like mice rats cats dogs and
things like that it wasn't actually
until
1954 that we started to unravel the
properties or the mechanisms behind a
single muscle fiber contraction Huxley
and Huxley to independent scientists I
think this is so great is one of my
favorite stories ever Sir Andrew Huxley
actually won a Nobel Prize for his work
in connecting the connective tissue and
cardiovascular system with muscle
contraction and central nervous system
and things like that but these were two
doctors interested in muscle physiology
both separately names Huxley not related
working independently came together
realize they were both close to making
the same break in science and published
a series of papers and I believe nature
and and with the most seminal one coming
in 1954 that described was called the
sliding filament theory this is the
basic idea of how most of contraction
now we won't get into in this video but
this is effectively the exact same
theory we teach in schools to this day
all right so over 50 years later they
nailed the exact mechanisms of skeletal
muscle fiber contraction
but again this is all in animal models
we had not yet gained access to human
muscle tissue so while this was a great
theory and probably fairly close we know
that there are tons of species to
species differences in everything and
particularly in muscles so while that
we're pretty sure this was how rat
tissue contracts we weren't exactly sure
the properties of humans and that stayed
this way until 1962 when a famous
researcher named Bergstrom reintroduced
the skeletal muscle biopsy procedure it
had been done way back in the 80s before
but it was essentially said okay you
know what we're not okay with this
property of this process anymore stop
doing it but in 1962 Bergstrom came
along and said okay I think we can do
this process in humans and this will
allow us to actually study human tissue
because all the work prior to this had
to be done in cadavers you couldn't
access live healthy skeletal muscle
tissue at best you could get some
surgery tissue but again that's a
problem because it may be someone was
sick on medications not healthy as the
point so I think this is really awesome
this is I got this directly from a
fantastic paper but it describes a
little bit of what the muscle biopsy
procedure looks like so you can here see
here this would be an actual muscle
biopsy needle this would be going into
the muscle belly itself and you can see
there's a little suction that you can
attach to the end of it so the needle
enters the muscle you pull the suction
which brings in all of this little
tissue right here into that bevel then
you have a blade and it doesn't look
like that
essentially sliced down right there and
then you remove the needle so anything
in that bevel area then comes home in
the needle with the researcher and
although it's slightly different it's
pretty close to exactly how we use the
process today all right so you can see
me over here by op Singh an individual
and I don't for legal and other reasons
I can't show you the actual
breaking of the needle into the skin but
this is actually what it looks like this
is a needle that we use to this day and
that's the piece of muscle sample that
we would extract from it that's probably
no no maybe a hundred milligrams of
tissue into which we would get maybe
several thousand individual muscle
fibers you can see over here this is the
same sample just pulled out of there and
put into a petri dish in my colleague
dr. Jimmy Bagley who's phenomenal at
this stuff and runs an excellent website
and an excellent laboratory on muscle
physiology
in humans you can see him processing the
tissue here so what he's really doing is
is aligning the fiber so you see how it
comes in right here kind of all jumbled
up and rolled together he's over here
he's clearing things like that which are
maybe some interstitial connective
tissue or some fatty deposits he kind of
gets those out of the way and he just
kind of processes the tissue so it's all
lined up nice and straight so when we
study it later it's not all rolled
together and balled up
okay now that we've got the basics of
muscle down let's talk about these fiber
types as I mentioned earlier the white
cylinder all used to represent a single
individual fast muscle fiber and a red
cylinder is a single slow fiber well if
we use this picture right here this
black cylinder this giant black one to
represent one individual muscle what we
see happens is it's built up of several
million probably if not hundreds of
thousands of individual muscle fibers
and what we see most importantly here is
the individual muscle is comprised of
bull fast and slow twitch so we have
some random comment why I should say
random but some combination or a
percentage of fast in other words some
of your muscles might be 50% fast twitch
50% slow twitch some might be 80/20 some
might be ninety ten or some combination
in between
so if i zoom in on one of the fibers and
it doesn't matter that I picked fast is
could be slow and so just imagine that
red cylinder and I'm zooming all the way
in what we see is the individual fiber
is made up of two really important
filaments all right these are called
actin and myosin
now the myosin is bigger it's often
called the thick filament the actin is a
smaller one and what you can't really
see here is one individual myosin is
encompassed by six Ackman's in a 3d
perimeter alright so you've got one big
thick myosin and all these actin
surrounding them and we'll go over a
little bit of the microstructure a
little bit more detail here in a second
but I'm gonna remove that red thing from
the background simply for your viewing
purposes but I wanted you to understand
that we've gone from the whole muscle
we've zoomed in and saw all these
different white and red fibers
everywhere now we're going to zoom in to
one of those individual fibers and it
doesn't matter again if it's a faster or
slow or otherwise
you remember this picture from earlier
in the video hopefully it caught your
attention but this is actually what it
looks like in real life so again my
colleague dr. Jimmy Bagley has pioneered
a technique where he can use confocal
microscopy these are laser microscopes
to take individual human muscle fibers
and to render them in three dimensions
and that's what you're literally seeing
here this was a real muscle fiber that
we took we laid in the scope we shot in
three dimensions and we're able to
reconstruct a 3d image of it so that
would be once muscle fiber there the
blue circles are what are called the my
own nuclei we'll talk about those in a
totally separate video but the nuclei
are what hold your DNA that's what
control your muscle fibers tell them to
grow shrink die and just as a side note
what makes humans particularly special
are our skeletal skeletal muscle at
least is we are not only the biggest
cells by volume and all of biology our
skeletal muscle but we're also one of
the few cell types that are multi
nucleated I almost all cells in the
entire universe and all of biology have
one nuclei per cell and look at how many
we have and you're not even seeing the
entire fiber there so this thing could
in theory be hundreds of microns long
longer with thousands of more fibers but
that's actually what it looks like
and in fact this isn't a realistic image
so this is the image that we made the
actual picture that we use to render
that 3d thing so what you're seeing here
is a very zoomed in portion of that
fiber and all the lines these diagonal
lines that are in red our fluorescent
tags that we put on to all of the actin
or dr. Bagley did at least and so you
can see the mirror you can yeah you
can't see the myosin unfortunetely and
the green stuff don't worry about but
that's how organized and how many of
these things exist in an individual
muscle fiber check back for the videos
later and we'll get more than perhaps
I'll get dr. Bagley in and he'll tell
you a little bit more about the
microstructure and some of the cool
stuff but that's an actual image of what
it would look like or what it does look
like
okay so now about this muscle
contraction thing if you've had your
undergraduate exercise physiology class
you should know this it can you come to
the back your hand but a lot of you out
there having that's a big reason why I'm
making these videos so I want you to
walk to walk you through this quickly
and if you were taught some minor
difference or detail who cares right
you're gonna get the gist of it
the sliding filament theory proposed by
Huxley and Huxley suggests that these
two filaments this actin and myosin or
would actually reach up grab each other
pull together and cause your entire
muscle to contract so a myosin is
sitting here it reaches up grabs an
actin it grabs another one on the other
side it pulls them both closer together
they come closer to the midline one
stacks on top of the other one and the
muscle of course then contracts so if I
were to take my bicep here and I were to
contract it like that what's happening
is the actin or overlapping or lys
coming closer together they're stacking
on top of each other so the muscle is
getting thicker and thinner so a little
bit more microstructure detail here
because in order to understand fiber
types have to understand this in fact
which we'll see in a second this is
exactly what fiber types are quick
twitch fibers versus slow twitch fibers
actually means that's what they are so
picture that we've got this myosin end
on the head of the myosin this little
fuchsia colored global is a molecule
called ATP this is the energy currency
of all of your cellular activity in
other words this is the fuel that it has
to have it's the gasoline for the engine
if you will so there's actually an ATP
molecule that can sit on the head this
myosin chain now through various
processes you're actually able to
split that ATP it's called hydrolysis of
ATP that gives you some energy in this
particular scenario that is an energetic
process where the breaking of the bonds
yields energy production and so we have
this excess energy and we use that to
back the myosin heavy chain head so
essentially like it's like if we were to
take those rubber band guns on your
finger right and you use the energy to
pull the rubber band actually back once
you've set it in place you're not
necessarily using energy all you have to
do to make that rubber band fire is to
get out of its way well that's
effectively what's happening here so you
split that ATP you take that energy to
the myosin heavy chain back so it's
sitting there and it's ready and cocked
position if a couple of things happen in
the cell that allow the myosin to grab
ahold of one of these green
actin globules
it'll grab ahold of them acting as soon
as it gets ahold of it it'll boom bring
it to the middle so that's kind of what
I'm representing here and yes I did skip
several steps there but I don't think
you necessarily care or need to know for
this particular talk so you watch the
animation the ATP splits all right
calcium comes into play it causes this
conformational change in the actin to
expose the binding site to what's called
troponin and moves the tropomyosin of
the way as fancy we've seen the actin or
the myosin is actually allowed to bind
to the actin so it grabs it and it pulls
it there and it actually stays in that
position till you put another ATP on the
molecule you can wreak och it back all
right so now just imagine though that
the myosin is super thick and instead of
having two of these little glob you've
got you know thousands of them on one
myosin unit and you've got six actin
surrounding the myosin and so it's
constantly reaching up in three
dimensions grabbing and pulling letting
go grabbing and pulling it's just like
you'd pull a rope right so you grab it
pull it as close as you can grab it pull
it as close as you can let go reach for
further distance and you keep pulling
right what's gonna happen is the actin
on this side and the actin and this side
of your muscle are gonna get pulled
until they line up right next to each
other you can't go any further they're
not gonna go over top of each other but
you're gonna pull them all again and
that's what's gonna contract okay that's
the basic sliding filament theory that
these filaments slide past one another
or one another to cause a skeletal
muscle contraction
well now that we get that if we go a
little bit deeper into what causes or
what allows the myosin to go through
this process we're gonna actually start
to understand what fiber types mean and
specifically what that fast or quick
twitch and from now on I'm just gonna
use fast some people say quick but in
science it's fast twitch it's the same
thing though okay so if we go back to
this myosin contraction and we see that
ATP ATP molecule well we can't split or
break apart a bond without something
called an enzyme in this particular case
it's called ATP ace ace means it's an
enzyme and what the enzyme ATP ASE's job
is to split ATP
so
that's effectively known as myosin
ATPase now keep that in mind it's gonna
come in just play a part here in a
second as well as way down the road
there's also a function of this myosin
called the heavy chain this is kind of a
neck region down here we're gonna use
both of these in just a second to help
us understand where fiber types are and
down the road it'll help us totally
understand why the confusion exists so
whether or not they can change too fast
which or slow to it now that we
understand the basics of sliding
filament theory and how a fiber
contracts let's go back a little bit to
the beginning remember that histo
chemistry stuff that combination of
chemistry and histology where we can
study fibers or cells and understand
properties well the group in 1955 said
you know what what if we take some
animal tissue and we turn it on itself
and make it a horizontal we come through
then with basically a blade and make a
horizontal slice just across it like
that that'll actually enabled us to look
directly down on the tissue and just
like remember the pictures from leaving
hook from the beginning we can start to
characterize these individual muscle
fibers but look at the quality we can
get now and so they said okay we see
these different shapes and we're able to
identify
different sizes of fibers and in fact
what they started to do is run chemical
assays and other techniques on these
tissue pieces it started to realize
there's different enzymatic function in
them so some of them have different
enzymes are not different enzymes
necessarily but they have more of some
of these enzymes and less of some of
these other ones so at this point in
time in fact going all the way back to
the beginning the main way that we could
differentiate fibers was if they had
these different enzymatic profiles and
so what they would do in this particular
case is basically splash it with some
acid some different pa-ching and the
fibers would turn from the image that
you just saw those red to black and
white and so what the fibers were able
to what scientists were actually able to
do is come through and say oh my gosh
for some reason when we give this entire
muscle the same acid treatment some of
the fibers turn white and some turn
black we don't necessarily even know
what this means but we'll just call the
the white ones white or the white ones
type one and the black ones type two now
you could get very confused on this
because people will flip-flop whether
they call black fibers type 1 or type 2
or white fibers type 1 or type 2 it
doesn't matter it really just depends on
which chemistry you use so don't worry
about that detail at all you just know
that if they turn one color they are one
type and they're another color their
type two you have to understand though
at the time
scientists didn't have the perspective
that we have now they didn't know fast -
it's a slow touch they drew is like I
don't we don't know what's going on
we're just going to call how do we
differentiate this fiber these white
ones from these black oh no well this
one this type is one and this type is
the second type and that's what that
name came from type 1 and type 2 it's
this type in that type alright so what
they would do with histo chemistry based
fiber typing is they would say okay
let's let's take a picture like this and
let's count a hundred fibers so we go
through in with circle you know one of
these and two of the 1-2-3 and we count
however many were type one and however
many were type two and you'd get a
profile so if you counted one hundred
total fibers and sixty five of them were
type one 60 and 45 of them were type -
you'd be 65 percent type one forty five
percent type two pretty simple process
right well this is what really launched
understanding of fiber types this is
where that term or that nomenclature
comes from
well what we now know is that histo
chemistry that pH staining technique is
actually
identification of the ATPase molecule so
what we now know is that some ATPase
molecules are much faster than others
they're able to split that ATP to allow
the muscle to contract a lot faster to
go back to restart and do it again and
so this now becomes known as ATPase
histo chemistry fiber typing on any
combination of those words if you see
the word type if you see ATPase if you
see see staining if you see histo
chemistry it's referring to classifying
or organizing these muscle fibers based
on the type of ATPase they have because
we know that that will reflect the speed
at which it can contract so we can call
it a now a quick twitch or a fast twitch
fiber all that's pretty synonymous now
alright so muscle ATPase was our
original way to differentiate between
the fibers
it didn't take them very long in fact it
took them just a couple of years after
the reintroduction of the biopsy to then
put the picture together and go oh my
gosh we didn't see it but now we see it
what is a type 1 fiber is also a slow is
also a red one and this is when they
really connected the dots between the
enzymatic profile the phenotype the
genotype what's it look like what color
is it physically how does it contract
and what's it called based on this
staining process this is where we really
launched our understanding that oh my
gosh we can use ATPase or the assistive
chemistry process to predict single
muscle fiber function and perhaps this
is important because some of them are a
lot faster and a lot slower than others
and as we reflect back to what we said
earlier remember human skeletal muscle
is different because every single one of
your muscles has at least some fast
twitch and at least some slow twitch but
prior to 1962 we didn't realize this
because in animals and one a quick
example in the rat life I believe the
soleus of a rat is generally 100% slow
twitch you won't find 100% slow twitch
of any muscle in the human body the
soleus is close is generally like 80%
slow twitch in contrast the EDL in in
mice or in rats it can be a hundred
percent fast twitch and you'll probably
never find any skeletal muscle on human
100% pass to it so we're unique like
that which makes us exciting and
difficult to study right doing human
research is always a pain in the ass for
this reason and many many others with
all this information in mind
research into muscle fiber typing
exploded so if we go back to this
original histo chemistry stuff and
remember the black fibers would be type
one or the white fibers would be type
two or whatever it happens to be well it
took them just a couple of years from
these original studies in the mid to
early 1960s to expand down say ow
actually if we change our methodology a
little bit so we use a slightly
different pH or we use it a couple of
different preparatory or finished steps
we get an image much more like this so
instead of all fibers being either dark
black or pure white what we see is
indeed we have these white fibers and we
have these black or dark fibers but we
start to get more specificity or more
resolution
for example what's that fiber
now this is when they first started to
realize oh we've got a major problem
so see before it was easy black white 55
of this 45 of these done well now it's
clear there's some clear blacks and some
clear whites
but what do I call that one you see if
there's only type 1 and type 2 I've got
to make a decision you know that's black
or that's white one of the two and the
reality of it this is how science works
you're gonna trace thousands of these
fibers and you're gonna categorize them
and more more than realistically some
graduate students gonna do this so some
point you is a busy investigator who
have spent your career on this and
hundreds of thousands of dollars is
gonna have to make that leave the
decision-making of whether or not this
fiber is a faster of slow-twitch up to
some graduate student who's trying to
decide whether or not that level of gray
is closer to white than it is black
and what gets even more difficult is
look at fibers like the one right here
what about out here what about out here
you can see now there's these different
levels of greatness and so they started
to started thinking well maybe there's
more than simply fast or slow twitch
maybe there's something in between so in
1969 a group can effectively came out
and said hey look folks we need to
reconsider this type 1 versus type 2
this fast versus slow twitch fiber
typing theory so in 1970 actually in a
famous study by Brooklyn Kaiser they
came out and said ok look we know type 1
is slow and type 2 is fast but we're
actually proposing is a type 2 C well
which we'll call an intermediate okay
now what we also realize is there are
multiple types of these type twos so
there's a type 2a and a type 2b and
specifically the type to wait and a type
2b are closer related to each other than
they are to the C into the type 1 and
that's why on my on the screen here I
have this even spacing between a 1 a 2 C
and a 2 a 2 B because we realized there
was slow twitch there was intermediate
and then there was two different types
of really closely related but clearly
distinguishable fast twitch now if
you're ever wondering why like why does
it go type 1 - C - a - B it's because of
what I just laid out it was the order of
discovery so we identified that this
these fast fibers were twos and then
realized oh there's multiple kinds of -
so we'll call it type 2 a and type 2 be
and then after that's when they found
type to see and so dove said of naming
it like one a or something they called
it type to see but it's actually closer
to type one and then it got the order a
lot of Wax so that's exactly how science
happens unfortunately it gets confusing
because they didn't know right and they
they were making the best decisions they
could when new information came out and
that's what science is really all about
so now up to 1970 we're like okay
there's fast slow intermediate and
actually a couple of different types of
fast and in fact if we summarized up to
nineteen seventy here's a couple of
points that we basically knew that
number one fiber type
was dependent upon the myosin ATPase
contractile velocity and number two we
have identified four distinct types when
we use histochem so chemistry staining
we've got black white apparently gray
and in like gray or something like that
what happened next revolutionized our
understanding of human muscle fiber
types and this was a technological
advancement from the use of histo
chemistry to determine muscle fiber type
to the use of the process called gel
electrophoresis
now to understand that remember how
we've got these four indistinct fiber
types well a fantastic paper came out in
1971 and I love this by the author Guth
or guff I'm not sure how to pronounce it
but they basically came out and said
look you're arbitrarily assigning or
identifying these fibers as a type one
or A to B or a double D or whatever the
hell you call it but really we should
start thinking about these as simply
being on a continuum we have the slowest
twitch over here the fastest switch over
here and everything else is some
arbitrary place in the middle we don't
have distinct sharp stops and starts we
really have a blend a transition from
red to white and in fact I'll use their
words because I love this quote that
they say quote fiber types are simply
too dynamic and flexible and what
they're referring to here is in order to
type them or to label them or categorize
them as these different types we
shouldn't do that because the types
themselves are too dynamic and flexible
when I say flexible I don't mean that
the fiber is literally elastic or
stretchy what they're referring to here
is the plasticity of it not being a
plasticity being a phrase we often use
in muscle physiology to describe tissues
ability to change adapt respond grow
shrink and do things like that so what
they're saying here is already laying
the foundation for the ability for the
understanding that hey these muscle
fiber types are probably quote dynamic
and flexible meaning they're probably
changing right so we can categorize them
and classify them as type 3c effort or
whatever we want to call them but
they're really just on this continuum
keep that in the back your mind until
later so a little bit more about this
electrophoresis process so unlike histo
chemistry where we would take the
individual muscle turn it on its side
and make that cross-sectional cut look
down on us so that we can analyze the
way each of those individual fibers
responds to the staining here we're
gonna use what's called a homogenous so
that's the entire sample so we would
take an entire muscle take a chunk out
of it put that entire chunk into a vial
or or a small tube we would take that to
homogenized it which means grind it all
up and it with some chemicals right and
the chemicals that we would specifically
use here are going to put a negative
blanket around the proteins and so
they're all ground-up mixed mashed
together so if there's a hundred or 300
different fibers in there the ground
together and each of the individual
proteins are would have gone through a
process what we call denaturing which is
basically meaning unfolding of the
protein and the chemicals we put in
there that you're seeing me represent
with a red color here again wrap a
little- blanket around the individual
proteins all right with that in mind we
all understand basic electrophoresis we
just don't know it right most of us
identify when we have a positive charge
and negative charge what happens all
right so two molecules or two atoms that
are the same charge are going to repel
and that are the exact or sorry the same
charge you have repelled and opposites
attract right so a negative will attract
the positive but two negatives will push
each other away so with that
understanding we can take that
individual sample take a couple of
pieces of glass pour gel in between it
and we're talking just a literal gel
like you'd use hair gel or something
like that but a little thicker we poke
little individual lanes in the gels like
you can see here which that allows us to
then say take some of that sample
pipette it out insert it into that
individual lane and put some electrodes
on these glass plates so we put a
negative electrode here and a positive
electrode there so what happens in is
once that is in certain we put the
switch on and turn on the electrical
part of this phoresis system since
there's negative charge at the top
negative charge around the proteins it's
going to push the protein away which
pushes it down the gel at the same time
we've got a positive charge at the
bottom that's pulling it down towards it
all right this is vertical gel
electrophoresis
okay well what that allows us to do then
is to realize that hey you know what
bigger proteins are gonna go through
that gel at a lot slower pace some other
proteins will fly further so if I put
all the proteins in one lane at the same
time remember I homogenized all the Fast
and Slow to fight food drivers together
I put them in the same Lane I turned
them on and turn the whole electricity
off at the exact same time I can then
look at my gel and the the bigger
proteins should be higher vertically on
the gel and the slower proteins should
be further down up because they would
Transpac through that gel at a faster
rate since we fixed time we'll be able
to then say okay take a look at an image
like this which is a classic gel image
and say you know what this these
proteins down here in this dark band
those are obviously all the smaller
proteins because they went further and
so this really introduced a different
method of typing based on what we'll
call science but in actuality is
molecular weight of the ATPase or myosin
heavy chain molecule and then we can
come back and still say look type 1 is
slow right so we know that the amount of
proteins on here are slow the amount
here are fast and the amount here are
also fast again this is supported this
the earlier comment that the two fast
twitch fiber types a and B were closer
together even though they are clearly
distinct they have an actual distinct a
totally different molecular weight size
then but they're there they're distinct
but they're closer to each other than
they are the type ones and you can see
that laid out here in this classic
electrophoresis gel image
in
order to get your fiber type profile
here so unlike histo chemistry when it
is a basic distribution so you have 50
type ones 50 type 2s you're 50/50 you
would do a similar thing but you would
use some software to say ok of all the
darkness in this picture and or in this
portion in this portion of this portion
what percent is occupied by each one so
in this particular image for example you
can see that this band looks a little
bit darker than this band and it's maybe
similar to this so you may say something
like you are I don't know 35% type 1 35%
type 2 and then the remaining what 30%
is type 2 B and so you can measure the
darkness of each band and you calculate
a percentage of each type occupying the
entire sample and you get some random
distribution like that
well with this information in mind
scientists were actually able to go back
to histo chemistry use specific
antibodies tagged those original one to
see 2a 2b fibers and in fact confirm
that oh my gosh when we have a very
specific fiber type it actually has a
different myosin component in fact not
only are they specific and distinct they
probably differ by size and probably
more accurately by size and the myosin
heavy chain will talk about the size of
the whole fiber a little bit later so
don't get those two things confused size
of the heavy chain or size or speed of
the ATP's with the size of the
individual cell or fiber itself
all right so remember histo chemistry
used the ATP a stain well what we're
electrophoresis is doing now is using
the heavy chain so it's not identical
but it's very very similar and some
would argue more accurate depending on
what you're looking for
okay so summarize the muscle fiber
typing methods so that we can move
forward answer our questions to figure
out why people argue over this stuff
even though we have a very very clear
answer so histo chemistry was that hum
was that cross sectional area where we
stain that we get our four different
types remember our 1 2 C and 2a 2b
electrophoresis was a little bit
different use we use a moderate tissue
sample and we get three different myosin
heavy chains now if you've ever read
anything into this field specifically if
you're an undergraduate or graduate
student and you've tried to read muscle
fiber typing research at this point you
might notice something two things stand
out on your tongue on the screen right
now number one the names and quotation
when we type a fiber based on histochem
astray that's when we refer to it as a
type
hopefully you remember the beginning of
the video I explained to you why we
literally call them types so if you read
a paper and you're seeing the
nomenclature type that almost always
denotes that they used histo chemistry
so it's a quick cheat right there or
it's a hack if you will if they use the
phrase MHC or sometimes m capital M
little Y HC that usually means they're
using electrophoresis as their type and
and that's why it's important to
understand this is because although the
two histo chemistry and gel
electrophoresis are very similar one
looks at ATPase and one looks at heavy
chains so it is different and in science
that part that level of distinction is
important all right so that's why if
you're reading inmate C's or types
that's what they're doing hopefully that
helped I know that probably saved a lot
of you some heartache as you're getting
your lit reviews and other things
prepped
another thing that should jump out at
you though
what happened to the two c's
how do we go from the histo chemistry
which gave us one - C - a - B - the gel
electrophoresis which only gave us one -
a into B and
the next little section I'm gonna answer
and solve that mystery as
you can imagine you aren't the only one
curious about this so a fantastic group
of scientists in 1988 he came along and
said okay again let's take a look at
this pistol chemistry based typing
directly compared to this heavy chain
electrophoresis based typing and what
they noticed was this
those type ones and those type two ways
and those type two bees notice how
they're all different colors here I'm
using that to distinguish how the
myosins are different between the fiber
types well what they found was the type
2 C's were in fact not a separate type
of myosin
but we're actually a combination of the
type 1 and the 2a so instead of calling
them a type 2 C meaning giving them
their own
fiber type distinction what's probably
more accurate to do is to describe them
as a
hybrid fiber now some of you that went
to school maybe in the you know 10-15
years ago or more you remember being
taught this type to C or you remember
hearing this type to C or in fact I
should probably say some of you that are
being taught information from that era
because you may still have heard that
recently that's where the term
intermediate came from well it's all the
way back to the to C fact some
scientists still use it to this day and
it's not inaccurate histo chemistry is
not wrong it's just a different
classification form all right so what we
like to think of it is is you've got
your type one which is a pure fiber type
2a and 2b those are all pure the one in
between the intermediate fiber is
actually a hybrid it is a composite it
is a portion type one and a portion type
two just like you would call your
automobile that is half gas half
electric is a hybrid car right the same
thing happened in 1980 with the muscle
fiber types
in fact I just have sort of told you a
lie something I just told you wasn't
completely honest I said it's half gas
half electric well that's not how muscle
fibers work in fact in that same study
or in another sense that they started to
realize that these hybrid fibers aren't
necessarily 50/50 split between 1 and 2
way they might be 75 25 25 75 73 and a
half whatever and a half that is twenty
three and a half or twenty two and a
half or whatever it is right that those
intermediate fibers are just at some
point some level of intermediate they're
not necessarily clean fifty-fifty so it
could be 25% one way seventy-five the
other or vice versa and in fact the
authors suggested that what's probably
happening is one of these hybrid fibers
is probably a pure fiber caught in mid
transition
this is another piece of information
that started to really support the idea
that muscle fiber types can change if
you didn't catch that animation I'll do
it one more time
this author's suspected that hey maybe
we've got a type one fiber and when we
biopsied that fiber was on its way to
being transitioned into a type two a so
we caught it at some random percentage
had we biopsied them a week later or two
weeks before instead of the fiber be in
fifty-fifty it might have been 49 51 or
forty sixty or something like that so it
is a type one fiber that is on its way
to becoming a type two a fiber you dis
caught it in transition or for that
matter it could be a to a transitioning
its way to being a type one we really
don't know all we know is we caught it
in transition I
love this because they paid homage to
the work from about a decade before when
they came in and in quote a classic the
classification of fibers into fiber
types is somewhat artificial those
certainly useful so what they meant by
that is saying look all of these are
just on a spectrum again like the the
goth article the Guth article though
they did recognize this does provide us
with some random usefulness or some
usefulness I should say you could this
is akin to why do we have a month why do
we separate our calendar in two weeks it
becomes easier for us to manage our life
to plan to organize the schedule the
world if we have we can break it all the
way down into these very small
sunrises Sun Goes Down will package
those in two days of seven will package
those in two days are roughly thirty
will package those into groups of twelve
we'll call that a year perfect now have
some astrological distinction between
those but the reason we call it a month
or not is really pretty arbitrary
but it is useful
so I'll give you an analogy of these
typing systems if we were to take this
picture right here and I asked you look
we're trying to improve traffic and then
folks that live in my area of the world
which is Southern California you can
certainly empathize with this picture
right unfortunately we see this way too
often nonetheless if I were to take you
and say hey look we're trying to improve
traffic in this area but before we can
improve traffic I need to understand
what the problem is who's driving there
what's it looking like once we identify
that we can try to come up with
strategies and solutions for the traffic
problem if you were to use histo
chemistry you would count you would go
ahead and say okay look I'm gonna
categorize all the the traffic here into
either being a truck car or a bike and
in this particular case you would count
all the individual trucks and you'd say
okay there are 50 trucks 35 cars and 15
bikes and you know what in some cases
that might be enough that might be an
accurate depiction if you're trying to
just simply generally describe what's
going on
with histo chemistry though remember
we don't have a clear answer between
what a car is and what a truck is so
just like we didn't know what was black
or what was dark earlier we got dark and
dark ish and gray and grayish sure and
in grayer and things like that it would
be a kindess thing okay we have trucks
that are black over here we've got cars
that are clearly a 2 egg which are white
and we've got type 2 bees which are
clearly a fast which and will clearly
call those a motorcycle
but what do we call those cars
what do you call this thing is that a
truck or is that a car it is kind of
grayish I'm probably closer to a truck
than it is a car but there's some
functions of an SUV that are more
car-like and like gas mileage and things
like that but some functions that are
more truck like
what do you certainly call this thing
right it is definitely a car in the
front and a truck in the back it is
actually partially black on the bottom
and then partially greater on the top
what do you call that with histo
chemistry you'd have to make a binary or
trinary
answer here and you'd say this is a car
and again if we were simply trying to
describe automobiles to an alien you
might say oh there's cars and trucks and
that might be good enough for your
answer but if I'm trying to really solve
complicated issues I can't say that
these two cars are a truck or a car or
in fact I can call these two automobiles
the same thing it wouldn't be specific
or accurate enough
making the problem even worse
what do you call a car like that
right that's certainly not a half car
half truck that might be more like a
half car half motorcycles sort of and
greyish and they get even further off
the reservation what the hell are things
like this all right this isn't even
though up here this one it's not even
black or white at all it's got colors
that's totally out it's a truck but it's
a super truck and then I don't know what
we call the Batmobile right it's
certainly part motorcycle part airplane
and we're just everywhere right and so
we come to realize again this no
chemistry is great and for the book for
the specific purposes of fiber typing
perhaps there's some limitations here if
we're trying to be extremely accurate
now histo chemistry has a ton of other
really important uses but simply for the
sake of fiber typing perhaps it leaves
us with a bit of inaccuracy
the gel homogenates are a little bit
different so if we took that same exact
traffic scenario and we tried to
categorize them so that we could give
our Department of Motor Vehicles
something useful our department
transportation probably we wouldn't type
it based on distribution in other words
how many cars how many trucks there are
what we would do is okay we're going to
classify categorize cars based on their
weight so and then we wouldn't call it a
car truck don't care at all if it's an
SUV or whatever it is if it's over three
times that I'm just making three tonnes
up as an example is it three tonnes or
is it less than three tonnes all right
so we would give a distribution this
percentage of the cars weighed more than
three tonnes is percentage weighed three
times and this percent made less than
three tonnes so what we can see is
although it is
different than histo chemistry it's
actually not that much more accurate
right because we're still learning the
problems like this in this scenario this
automobile right here whatever this
little spaceship thing is would be
categorized as the exact same thing as a
motorcycle
from the far out maybe we don't care but
if we're really trying to differentiate
and try and solve a problem if we want
to be as accurate and specific as
possible that's simply not going to fly
so although we thought histochem
asserted we thought gel electrophoresis
is that the montant level was an answer
a solution to our great grayish darker
problem we took all the arbitrariness
out of it
and we still realized we've got some
major problems here
same thing with here right these two
automobiles would be categorized as the
exact same thing and we just simply know
that's not true but what if this we took
that subjectivity out of the histo
chemistry we eliminated that portion of
it we stuck with our gels but instead of
trying to categorize all of these fibers
at once or all of these cars at once we
said okay we're gonna we're gonna make a
traffic stop we're going to make every
single automobile passing by stop and we
will analyze it one fibre at a time
based on its weight
right and so we could go through this
car up here and say no that's not a
truck that's a van that's a different
category well this is a type of car but
it is a car with a hatchback cool this
is acid you get the idea here right this
is what's called single fiber gel
electrophoresis it's that same refreezes
process but instead of doing it on the
entire tissue that himand in it where we
grind it all up together we pull out one
muscle fiber at a time and we categorize
it and type it at that level of detail
so what it would look like would be
something like this we would start with
our entire muscle sample but instead of
putting the entire thing into that tube
and grinding it all up we'd pull out one
muscle fiber at a time that would get
ground all up the exact same processes
before- blanket put in the gel then we
repeat and we draw out hundreds of the
muscle fibers and in fact what I've done
is made a little video for you so you
can see it playing right here so I've
dyed the entire muscle sample in a green
called the RNA later so that you can see
it so that's you know several dozen
muscle fibers watch up here that's me
pulling out two individual fibers and it
comes out just like that I have my
undergraduates doing this by the way
it's not that complicated you'll see me
separate the two fibers
like that right there and in fact just
so you can see it a little bit more
clarity I'll take my two tweezers and
break off one of the fibers in half so
you can see right there
alright now what that does is that
allows me to isolate individual muscle
fibers
so I would take that sample that I just
pulled from right down here and I would
put it in
that well and I would continue to do
this until I had pulled several hundred
thousand or however many individual
fibers I need now in this particular
case instead of the entire sample
getting that Lane only one fiber gets
its own individual Lane so when I run my
analysis I get to determine the
molecular weight of the individual
muscle fiber so what actually happened
earlier with the homogenous is say I had
a hundred fibers in that entire bundle
that I put into one gel that doesn't
actually tell me that the distribution
the number of individual fibers that are
a certain type it just tells me how much
of each fiber type is represented in the
entire sample than other words if I had
ten to a fibers and ten or just one
let's make it easy ten slow and ten fast
I wouldn't necessarily see that in the
homogeneous gel because if the ten fast
fibers were ten times bigger
the band
density would be ninety percent to a and
ten percent type one so really what it's
giving me is called a percent area
occupied so of the entire muscle what
percentage is occupied by fast fiber
types not necessarily the distribution
now we could argue later what's more
important percentage of area occupied or
fiber distribution but nonetheless
this is the inherent problem with the
homogeneous stuff and a single fiber
electrophoresis eliminates that problem
so our gel would look something like
this in this case we've got six
individual fibers we would go through
the same process as before the slow ones
would migrate further down the gel so
these individuals would be one muscle
fiber on the far left that's a type one
this would be one muscle fiber that's
also type one this would be a two-way
right here and up there would be a to
beat writes the fastest it would be
further up the gel and then we go on the
nether two fibers and so what would
actually happen is we would calculate a
distribution percentage like we did with
them the histo chemistry actually from
earlier and we'd say okay let's say we
typed six fibers now in reality if we
wanted to get an actual answer we would
probably type several hundred fibers but
just to make it easy all of these six
fibers what we figured out is say two of
them are type one three of them are 2a
and one of them is type 2b so you'd be
33% slow to which 50% to a and 17% to B
right now with that we would assume that
the the biopsy sample we got reflects a
normal sample of the entire muscle so
then we would able be able to say things
like that particular muscle is x percent
fast-twitch x percent slow-twitch
remember earlier no humans have any
muscle that's 100% fast or slow it's
always a mix that's something like that
now there is differences between the
muscles so your hamstring muscle
compared to say your quadricep muscle
your hamstring muscles probably more has
a higher percentage of fast-twitch than
the slow but it's still not a hundred
percent fast which there are slow twitch
fibers and all of your muscles
now at this point you may be confused
where you no more than an hour in or
something like that now and we've been
calling them type to be fibers and some
of you may be thinking I thought they
were typed 2x
what happened was in 1994 a wonderful
study came out that suggested hey wait a
minute maybe these fibers we've been
calling to be are actually more like 2x
let me back you remember how we talked
about there was type ones originally
type twos and then we thought okay
there's two types of type twos there's a
type 1 or type 2 a and there's a type 2
B and then we eventually found those
type 2 C's but once we got rid of the
type 2 sees that left us with one - A to
B which we've been using throughout this
entire discussion well they did some
really interesting work in this
particular study and they used some
genetic typing along with this this
electrophoresis and found wait a minute
the fiber that we had been describing as
a type 2 B is
actually more analogous to the type 2 X
found in in rodents so in other words
humans and do do indeed have threes pure
fiber types 1 - a and what we thought
was to be but rodents have 4 1 2 A to B
and 2 X and what we had been calling a
tube B was actually a 2 X and so you can
see that very clearly here the 2 X that
we were able to use the genotyping and
to match with in the rodents was exactly
what we were seeing in humans and we in
fact did not have the to beat isoform
that was actually a separate faster yet
fiber type so this is where the
confusion entered and again if you've
learned this or heard this from a source
that wasn't privy to this information
even though it's been around since 1994
in fairness it is still prevalent in
textbooks online everywhere people talk
about the to be fibers well we can say
now conclusively there is no such thing
as a to be fiber in humans it is a 2 X
fiber okay
animals some rodents have to be in fact
we've done some work with bear tissue
before and other species that do have
separate fiber types from ours but we
can say now without really entered any
reservation that the correct term is 2 X
and so we're going to be using that from
now on
moving forward and so if we come back to
one of our gels and this was described
beautifully in a 1988 study we have
these pure type ones these pure two a's
in these pure two x's and remember the
hive we had earlier well it's actually
it's the more expanded now so again
these are individual lanes so what
you're seeing in the far left is one
muscle fiber using a single fiber
electrophoresis technique that's one
muscle fiber that is a pure type one
this is one muscle fiber that is a
hybrid some proportions type one some
proportions to way then there's a pure
type two way
next to that is another hybrid fiber
which is actually partially to a
partially two-x followed that by a pure
2x and then of course there is actually
the infamous triple hybrid which is one
fiber that Co Express is both fast slow
and the mega fast version so it's 1/2 a
+ 2 X in the same individual muscle
fiber now these ones in red here the one
to a the to a 2 X the 1 to a 2 X we
collectively call the hybrids and this
is critically important because we now
know that somewhere between 10 to 70
percent of all your muscle fibers are in
that current hybrid state so if we were
to try to do a study where the major
dependent variable or the major outcome
the measurement that we were interested
in was do muscle fiber types change or
not if we were not able to successfully
identify these hybrid fibers we would
miss or miss identify or miss label
anywhere between ten and seventy percent
of the fibers
obviously this is a major major problem
if we were just trying to create some
sort of general categorization some
unimportant or invariable then perhaps
we could get away with this nonspecific
methods of gel homogeneous or pistol
chemistry but if we really want to
answer the question of do they change
we've got to go for this single fiber
electrophoresis or something even more
advanced or we'll miss huge chunks of
our spectrum
going back a little bit to this Co
expression of a single fiber and filling
in this hybrid idea so we talked about
earlier we've known since the 60s and
70s that there are these hybrid fibers
in between and now they're not
necessarily 50% faster 50% slow that
there's some other random percentage
well this wonderful paper from two one
showed that very clearly using the
single fiber electrophoresis method they
were able to show that so for example
there could be a single fiber that would
be categorized as a one - a hybrid that
is a totally different percentage than
another fiber so up here on the left you
can see the image is quite clearly these
are two individual fibers one over here
on one over here they're both one - a
hybrids but in one of them the first one
it is 91% type-1 9% to a and the second
one is 75% to a 25%
type one and in fact we could go on and
on and on and in fact they showed two
different - a2x hybrids that were
different percentages one was more 2x
and two a there was the inverse and we
see the random distribution of the one
to a two axis this I think this paper
was really nice because it really
highlighted the fact that again we're on
this continuum right so in depending on
whether we need to know this or not it
is a bit arbitrary to categorize fibers
into these small differences in between
when we could probably just zoom back
all the way out and say there's fast and
slow and a bunch of hybrids are a bunch
of things somewhere in between so
to come back up and wrap this final bit
of story up on the fiber typing methods
so that we can move in to our answer of
do they change or not and talk about why
the confusion exists we need to add this
third fiber typing method to our summary
so we've got our single fiber
electrophoresis which combines a little
bit of both histo chemistry and the fact
that it is a single fiber one fiber at a
time analysis with the molecular weight
identification strategy of the
homogeneous gels or excuse me of the
electrophoresis gels and so that we're
able to actually now instead of getting
four types or three myosin heavy chain
x' we get three pure heavy chains and
three pure or three possible hybrids
okay so for the purposes of identifying
distribution we think this is very
clearly the most effective and in fact
research several studies from several
labs around the world have shown this to
be by far the most accurate and valid
and specific fiber typing method outside
of moving on to genotyping or something
like that
so if we were to take our final traffic
analogy to really sum things up here if
we were to use the gel single fiber
electrophoresis we would get something
more like this
some percentage of our automobiles are
over three tons because remember we're
still using electrophoresis so we're
still using a molecular weight based
typing approach
some percentage is between two and three
tons some percentages one two time you
get the idea down here right and what it
does is it allows us to be much more
specific and to give ourselves many more
categories as opposed to simply over
three towns under three tonnes or
something like that
so to wrap off section one when I told
you at the very beginning here when you
finish this video you're gonna have
three things well hopefully by now you
understand a little bit more about what
fiber types actually are and what that
means all right so specifically refers
to differences in either the myosin
heavy chain size or the speed of
velocity of the ATPase and that they
exist on a continuum from the slowest
type one to the fastest type two X in
the next section we'll finally talk
about do they change with training
you